<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of the royall commission of King Jesus. Mat. 28. 18.19.20. compared with Mark. 16. 15.16. Against the antichristian faction of Pope Innocensius the third, and all his favourits; that enacted by a decree, that the baptisme of the infants of beleevers, should succeed circumsion. Deret. Gre. l. 3. which doth vniversally oppose the commission, granted by King Jesus, Mat. 28.19. Goe teach and baptise &amp;c. by giving authority to all his preists, that receive ordination from him, to goe, and first baptise the infants of beleevers borne within the parish, and then teach them. Written (by Francis Cornewell Mr. of Arts, and sometimes student of Emanuell Colledge in Cambridge)...</title>
            <author>Cornwell, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80583</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859691</idno>
  <idno type="VID">111786</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240864754</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E10_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859691</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99859691e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 2:E10[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of the royall commission of King Jesus. Mat. 28. 18.19.20. compared with Mark. 16. 15.16. Against the antichristian faction of Pope Innocensius the third, and all his favourits; that enacted by a decree, that the baptisme of the infants of beleevers, should succeed circumsion. Deret. Gre. l. 3. which doth vniversally oppose the commission, granted by King Jesus, Mat. 28.19. Goe teach and baptise &amp;c. by giving authority to all his preists, that receive ordination from him, to goe, and first baptise the infants of beleevers borne within the parish, and then teach them. Written (by Francis Cornewell Mr. of Arts, and sometimes student of Emanuell Colledge in Cambridge)...</title>
                  <author>Cornwell, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed An. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 24. London.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Innocent, --  Pope, 1160 or 61-1216.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111786:1"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION OF THE ROYALL COMMISSION OF KING JESUS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MAT.</hi> 28.18.19.20. compared with <hi>MARK.</hi> 16.15.16.</p>
            <p>AGAINST THE ANTICHRISTIAN FACTION OF POPE <hi>INNOCENSIƲS</hi> the third, and all his <hi>Favourits;</hi> that enacted by a <hi>Decree,</hi> that the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme</hi> of the <hi>Infants</hi> of <hi>Beleevers,</hi> should succeed <hi>Circumsion. Deret. Gre. l.</hi> 3. which doth vniversally oppose the <hi>Commission,</hi> granted by <hi>King Jesus, Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Goe teach and baptise &amp;c.</hi> by giving Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to all his Preists, that receive <hi>Ordination</hi> from him, to <hi>Goe,</hi> and first <hi>baptise</hi> the <hi>Infants</hi> of Beleevers borne within the <hi>Parish,</hi> and then teach them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WRITTEN (BY</hi> FRANCIS CORNEWELL <hi>Mr.</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> and sometimes Student of <hi>Emanuell Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi>) out of his love and sinceare affection, he beareth to his native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen; who with him have taken a <hi>Protestation,</hi> and <hi>Solemne Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenant</hi> to oppose all <hi>Poperey,</hi> and <hi>Popish Innovations;</hi> And to stand for a <hi>Reformation in England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> according to the Word of God; that his and their consciences may be freed from that guilt, misery, and curse, that otherwise is falling on them: as Mr. <hi>Case</hi> a <hi>Learned Synodian</hi> testifieth in his Sermon styled, <hi>A Covenant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed for the pacification of the quarrell:</hi> viz. <hi>that the Sword shall goe through the Land to avenge the quarrell of the Covenant page</hi> 27. 28.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I am come in my Fathers Name, amd yee receive me not: if an other shall come in his owne name, him yee will receive.</p>
               <bibl>John <hi>5.43.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Approved of by the Church of Jesus Christ; that is called, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by the Power of <hi>King Jesus</hi> according to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. Printed <hi>An.</hi> 1644.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111786:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111786:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE House of Commons assembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> sad and vnnaturall bloody Tragedies of our times may not vnfitly be compared, to the <hi>two Women</hi> striving for a Child, <hi>1</hi> Kin. <hi>3.</hi> ch. one clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it as her owne; the other saith, Nay; but it is mine: the contention is so hot, that King <hi>Solomon</hi> calleth for a sword; giveth out the Word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; <hi>Divide:</hi> Content saith the Harlot, let it be neither mine, nor thine, but divide it: but the true Mothers bowels yearned upon her son, and said, oh my Lord, give her the living child: shee could endure no division: Such (Right Honourable) is the controversie in our Land. The malignant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie pretend to fight for a Christ, and in their blind zeale they will dye too, but they will enjoy him. And you (thrice worthy Patriots) in all your Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons say so likewise. Now the Lord to decide the Controversie, permitteth the Sword to come, and crieth aloud in our Land; <hi>Divide.</hi> Content, saith the Antichristian and malignant partie: Christ, and their Arch-Bishops, Arch-Deanes, Deanes, Preists and Deacons, and all Ecclesiasticall persons depending vpon them: Christ, and their devised worship, Temples, Alters, Tythes, and Offerings: Christ, and the residue of their Fore-fathers Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: thus let them but enjoy a divided Christ, and there will be an end of Controversie. But they (Right Honourable) that are holy, synceare, faithfull and true Covenanters with you (according to the light they have received) even in all the three Ilands, will have an whole Christ, or no Christ; their faithfull soules cannot endure to run division: a Christ, they must have in all his Offices: Christ to be their King, and his Commission to be maintained, Mat. <hi>28.18.19.20.</hi> least otherwise he make good his Word against vs, Luke <hi>19.27.</hi> Christ their Prophet, whom they will only heare (as the Father from
<pb facs="tcp:111786:3"/> Heaven chargeth vs to doe, Mat. <hi>17.5.</hi> And Moses truly said to the Fathers, him shall ye heare in all things, he shall say vnto you: And it shall come to passe, that everie soule, which will not hear that Prophet, shall be destroyed from amongst the People, Act. <hi>3.22.23.</hi> And all Traditions of men, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, as holy Paul recordeth, Gal. <hi>1.8.9.</hi> Christ their Preist; and no Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, but him only, <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>2.5.</hi> that the Lord Jesus may be one, and his name one, in the three Kingdomes; that we, and our posterity after vs may live in faith and love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the midst of vs. Now the cheife cause and roote of all our division, is from the Roman Hierarchie, who have made a Law, that whosoever shall interpret, or give the sence of the holy Scriptures, contrary to their determination, they must remaine Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma; and the Furnace did burne then hottest against the Saints, when the Civill Magistrate (that is appoynted of God for the praise of them that doe well <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>2.14.</hi>) joyned their power with Romes proud Bishops and Preists, to persecute, and kill all them, that would not submit to the Roman Jurisdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Hence arose all the Martyrdoms in England, from the time of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard the second, in whose time, the Prelats obtained a Law to kill the English Subjects, that would declare the whole truth (so farre as it was revealed t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them) and keepe a good conscience to God and man. Thus by penall Statutes, the popish English Prelats, and Preists did long tyrannize over the consciences of the godly and faithfull in the Land, that would not subject to their Decrees and humaine Traditions and corrupt Interpretations of the holy Scriptures: Hence it was that the thrice Noble and antient warlike Nation, our Brethren the Scots; when they contended for a Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the light they had received from the Lord, and casting of Romes proud, papall, and prelaticall Government, with all her devised Formes of Worship, they must dye: yea and the English Bishops with their High Preists will give large summes of money towards the leavying of an Armie; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense the King and Nobility to kill, and destroy them: yea when the Lord opened your eyes, with the eye-salve of his spirit (Thrice Deare and Noble Patriots) to make a solemne Protestation, to oppose all Popery, and Popish Innovations, and to extirpate Episcopacy root and branch: Then evill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell prevailed with the King to withdraw from his Parliament, and under pretence of a Guard to protect his Person, to make way against you, that you might dye: But our faithfull Nobles, and true hearted Commons in England reply; shall our Jonathans dye, who have in part freed our consciences from Roman Traditions; and Covenanted with vs for a pure Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:111786:3"/> to the Word of God and preserved our estates, and liberties from an Arbitrary Government: shall they dye, that have wrought such a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Land? They shall not dye; we will bleed our selves (before an haire shall fall from your heads) if either we with our persons, prayrs, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels, states, or swords can prevent it. Even so your pore Petitioner (Right Honourable) by eating a litle of the honey of Gods eternal truth his eyes have been opened to see and vnderstand, that the Royall Commission of King Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus extendeth no further, but to Beleivers, that are instructed in the faith by the Gospell, and they only to be baptized, Marke <hi>16.15.16.</hi> opposing the Decree of Pope Innocentius the third, that appoynted, that the Baptisme of the Infants of Beleivers should extend as farre, as Circumcision; thereby establishing Nationall Churches, and overthrowing the particular Churches of Jesus Christ, that are called out of the World by the preaching of the Gospell, Marke <hi>16.15.16.</hi> for the denying of which popish consequence (as my ensewing discourse will more largely demonstrate) J must dye, and be deserted of my freinds, and allies; yee and also J have received much injustice from some, that would be counted the Ministers of Christ, which have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved my Arguments from vnder my hand fairly written, this <hi>14.</hi> or <hi>15.</hi> monthes, with a promise, that if they should convince me from the word of God, that I was in an errour, I would willingly recant; yet I never received any satisfactory Answer from them. Wherefore (Right Honourable) you are the Sanctuary (next vnder Heavens protection) to flye vnto for Justice: Seeing you are joynt Covenanters with all them, that stand for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation according to the Word: For it is not the voyce of the Assembly, but Christ only in the Assemblyes, we have covenanted to listen to; as Mr Case testifieth in his Sermon styled, the Covenant renewed, pag. <hi>43.</hi> Oh consider! what a dangerous thing it is to praevaricate the least from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant your Honours have made: as Mr. Thomas Goodwin once admonished you in his Sermon on Zach. <hi>4.</hi> v. <hi>6.7.8.9.</hi> p. <hi>43.</hi> line <hi>30.31,</hi> pag, <hi>44.</hi> line <hi>1.2. 3.</hi> viz. For if you should build the least hay and stuble, you will not only suffer losse; but lay a Foundation of a new rent, and division in the age to come. David not carrying the Arke according to the due order of the God of Israel caused breach vpon Vzziah, <hi>1</hi> Cron. <hi>15.12.13.</hi> For God is so jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his Glory, that he cannot endure his Worship to be corrupted with the least mixture of man, Levit. <hi>10.1, 2.</hi> If the Reformation begun in the time of King Edward the sixt, and queen Elizabeth of happy memory, had been established according to that order, that King Iesus the great Prophet
<pb facs="tcp:111786:4"/> hath left vs a pattern for, in his Word; I am confident England had never seen this bloody day: Is not England like Egypt (you grave religious Patriots) almost destroyed; (Exod. <hi>10.7.</hi>) because the Lawes and Orders of Jesus Christ, the Great King of his Church is not observed: The Lord put it into your hearts to be like minded to noble Cyrus and Darius according to your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to give libertie of Conscience, to all such as know the Lord Jesus, and are ashamed of the abominations, that they have done in the Land of their spirituall Captivity vnder Antichrist, to build the spirituall House according to the Patterne (the Lord Jesus hath left vs) in his eternall truth, that we may pray for your peace, and the Kingdoms prosperity, Tim. <hi>1.2.1.2.</hi> And as for them that know not the Lord Jesus Christ, let them alone (as the Lord Jesus informeth you, Mat. <hi>15.14.</hi>) vntill God call them forth out of Mysticall Babylon, Rev. <hi>18.4.</hi> For none can perswade a pore <hi>Japhet</hi> (a pore <hi>Gentile,</hi> who is alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in him, Ephes. <hi>4.17.18.</hi>) to dwell in the Tents of Shem, but a God alone, Gen. <hi>9.27.</hi> least that Judgment befall the Kingdome, that <hi>Mr. Case</hi> hath threatned in his Sermon, called a Covenant renewed, page <hi>27.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours humble Servant, and Souldier,</hi> that hath hazarded his life for his Countryes Liberties; that is willing to be reformed, if he shall from the word of King Jesus, be righly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that he is in an errour; and humbly submit himselfe to your Honours Censure. <hi>FRANCIS CORNEWELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111786:4"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION Of the Royall Commission of KING JESUS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>He which saith J know him, and keepeth not his Commandements, (<hi>beleive, and be dipped,</hi> Marke <hi>16.16.</hi>) is a lyar and the truth is not in him, <bibl>
                     <hi>1</hi> John <hi>2.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HE which doth any thing doubtingly, is condemned in himselfe: For whatsoever is not of faith is sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. You therefore that are stronge, ought to informe the weake, ye that are mighty in the Scriptures, ought to instruct the ignorant: Least through your neglect you destroy him, for whom Christ dyed, <hi>Rom,</hi> 14.15. Oh that the learned of the Ministry (that are in Covenant with our Parliament Worthies, and the whole English Nation, for a Reformation agreable to the Word of our good God: And to Extirpate Popery, Prelacy, superstition, scisme, Heresy, and whatsoevr shall be found contray to sound Doctrine, and the power of godlynes) would rightly informe me, and resolve me this case of conscience, before it be condemned for Scisme, and Heresy; and my selfe for holding of it, be adjudged an Heretique; least for the neglect, that Judgment befall the Kingdome (that Mr. <hi>Case</hi> a member of the <hi>Synod</hi> threatned) viz. <hi>that the Sword should goe through the Land to avenge the quarrell of the Covenant:</hi> as his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in print testifieth, <hi>pag.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>That which God hath joyned together, no man ought to seperate.</p>
            <p>But Faith and Baptisme (or more properly Dipping) God hath hath joyned together.</p>
            <p>Therefore Faith and Baptisme (or Dipping as the Originall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it) no man ought to seperate.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111786:5"/>
            <p>Major is evident, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.6. <hi>what God hath joyned together let no man put asunder.</hi> To this Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> subscribeth (in the case of the unlawfulnesse for private persons to Baptize) in his Comentary on <hi>Galat.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>p.</hi> 262. <hi>n.</hi> 45.46.47.48.</p>
            <p>Minor is evident, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Beleive, and be Dipped. Acts</hi> 8.11.36.37.38. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>6.15.33.34. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.27. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>Oh that the learned English Ministrie would enforme me (least my blood like <hi>Abels crie</hi> loud to heaven, for vengance for not satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying a troubled conscience, that long hath laboured vnder this burthen) How J shall admit, or consent to the admittance of the Infant of a Beleiver to be made a visible member of a particular Congregation of Christs body; and Baptize, viz. <hi>Dippe</hi> it, before it be able to make his confession of his Faith and Repentance: Least J consent to seperate what God hath joyned together; and make my selfe accursed, <hi>Gal</hi> 1.7.8. And be rejected of all the Churches of Jesus Christ as scismaticall, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.18. Marke them which cause diuisions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and avoyde them: For they are such as serve not our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, but their owne bellys, and by good words and faire spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches deceive the hearts of the simple: For J speake only of visible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in of Members of particular Churches of Jesus Christ; and not of invisible; secret things belong to God, revealed things to vs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29.</p>
            <p>It is acknowledged, and confessed; that faith is required of men of yeares, that are to be admitted into a particular Congregation of Christs Body: But not in Infants who come from the loynes of beleiving parents. For they argue thus; As <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seed were circumcised, so the Beleiver and his seed must be baptized. Now I doe earnestly desire the Learned and faithfull in the Land (that are in (Covenant for a Reformation) to shew me what word of Christ they have to warrant this their consequence (seeing the Word of Christ according to our Covenant ought to dwell richly in us, to decide this controversie, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.) For my part I know none; though Antichrist hath, instance the Decree of <hi>Pope Innocentius</hi> the third, <hi>Decret. Gregor. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 42. c. 3. as Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> in his <hi>Synopsis Baptismi, de baptismo Infantium</hi> citeth.</p>
            <p>That whereas Circumcision (by the Commandement of God)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111786:5"/> was conferred vpon the Infants aswell as the Elder sort: So Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme also which succeedeth in roome thereof, and is more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to men and women must be conferred to both: vid. Infant, aswell as Elder sort.</p>
            <p>Now because I have taken a Protestation, to oppose all Popery, and popish Innovations, I doe deny this popish consequence, for these ensuing Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For the Circumcising of Infants, there was a precept from God to enjone it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. An example that <hi>Abraham</hi> circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised <hi>Isaac</hi> the eight day, as God commanded, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A prefixed day, to wit, the eight day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. <hi>he which is eight dayes old shalbe Circumcised.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 A penaltie imposed, <hi>the vncircumcised man-child whose flesh of his foreskin is not circumcised, that soule shalbe cut off from his people: He hath broaken my Covenant, Gen.</hi> 17.14.</p>
            <p>But for the baptizing of Infants into the spirituall House of the new Testament whereof Jesus Christ is Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. and Head, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.22.23. yea, and King, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. and Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.8. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22.23. For it is not the voyce of the Church, but Christ in the Church, that we have covenanted to hearken vnto, as Mr. <hi>Case</hi> his Sermon testifieth, <hi>pag.</hi> 48.43.</p>
            <p>Now there is no precept from this glorious Head, King, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to command it, nor any example in all the New Testament of any Beleivers Infant Baptized or Dipped; if there be, let the most learned in the Land shew it, and I will acknowledge I am in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and recant it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Neither is there any day appoynted when it shall be Dipped.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Nor any penaltie imposed (for it is Election saveth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant dying yongue and not Baptisme as Papists fonly teach, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>For the Children being not yet borne neither having done good nor evill, that the purpose of God according to Election may stand, not of workes, but of him that calleth.</hi> 11. <hi>It was said the Elder shall serve the yonguer:</hi> 13. <hi>As it is written Jacob have I loved, and Esaw have I hated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then I argue against <hi>Pope Innocencius</hi> the third and all his favorites.</p>
            <p>That which is not of faith is a sin to the Church that doth it,</p>
            <p>But the Baptizing (or rather the sprinkling) of the Infants of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111786:6"/> beleivers (as it is used) is not of faith.</p>
            <p>Ergo the baptizing (to wit, the sprinkling) of the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers is a sin to the Church that doth it.</p>
            <p>Major is evident, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Whatsoever is not of faith is sm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Minor thus. That which hath no precept, nor example out of the Scriptures for the doing of it, is not of faith.</p>
            <p>But the Baptizing (or sprinkling rather) of the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers hath no precept, nor example out of the Scriptures for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
            <p>Ergo, the baptizing (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers is not of faith.</p>
            <p>Major is evident: <hi>Mat</hi> 15, 19. ip <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.23. <hi>In vaine they worship me, teaching for doctrine the Precepts of men. If any man love me he will keep my words. Gal.</hi> 1.7. <hi>If I or an Angell from Heaven preach any thing, save that ye have received, hold him accursed.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4. To this subscribeth Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Coment: <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.27. in the case of the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse of private persons to baptise: <hi>pag.</hi> 262. <hi>lin.</hi> 48. 49. 50. 51. to wit, whatsoever is not of faith is sin, (now the Administration of baptisme by private persons is without faith; for there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precept nor example for in the Word of God.</p>
            <p>The Minor I doe earnestly desire the godly learned, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Land, to shew me; or else let them glorifie God in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the truth, as Mr. <hi>Marshall</hi> hath lately done in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.34. that the Sword may not may not goe through the Land for the avenging the quarrell of the Covenant, as Mr. <hi>Cases</hi> Sermon in print testifieth, <hi>pag.</hi> 27. 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Reason, why I oppose this popish consequence of <hi>Innocenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the third is this;</p>
            <p>That consequence which opposeth many of Gods divine truths contained in the inspired Scriptures is not of faith.</p>
            <p>But the popish consequence of baptizing (or rather sprinkling) the Infants of beleivers opposeth many of Gods divine truths contained in the Inspired Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Ergo, the popish consequence of baptizing (or rather sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infants of beleivers is not of faith.</p>
            <p>Major is evident: <hi>Esa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and the Testimony; If they speake not according to this word, it is because there is no light in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111786:6"/> them Ro.</hi> 16.17.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.4.5. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.10.11.</p>
            <p>Minor is evident: 1. Because this popish consequence of the baptisme (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of beleivers doth put an Infant into a state of grace and remission of sinnes, before cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: whereas calling in the Scriptures is the first meanes, by which God doth evidence to his Elect (whom he loved in Christ before the world began, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.) the riches of his love in pardoning their sinnes, and in giving them an inheritance among them which are sanctified by faith in Christ Jesus <hi>Ac.</hi> 26.18. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Heb,</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p>Because this popish consequence of the baptizing (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers doth constitute them visible members of the paricular Congregation of Christs body before calling, which opposeth the written Word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>yee are a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen generation, a royall preisthood, an holy Nation, a peculiar people, that you should shew forth the virtues of him that hath called you out of dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse into this marvelous light.</hi> 10. <hi>v. which in time past were not a people, are now the people of God; which were not vnder mere y, but now have obtained mercy, Ro.</hi> 1.6.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Because this popish consequence, of the baptisme (or sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infant of Beleivers doth make the materials of the spirituall House of the New Testament whereof Jesus is Head, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.22.23. to consist of dead stones; which opposeth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Ye as lively stones are built vp a spirituall House, an holy preisthood, to offer vp spirituall sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infants of Beleivers vpholdeth a Nationall Chucrh-state (as Circumcision did of old) which opposeth the Scriptures, <hi>Rev,</hi> 1.20. <hi>The seaven Candlestickes which thou sawest, are seaven Churches.</hi> To this Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> subscribeth: instance his Sermon preached before the Parliament on <hi>Zechary</hi> 4:6. <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church but one Candlesticke, the particular Churches seaven Candlestickes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers doth instate all the Infants of the beleeving Gentiles to be borne in a Covenant of grace, and to have a right to a promise of life in Christ Jesus: as Mr. <hi>Tho: Wilson</hi> affirmed in his Sermon at <hi>Maidestone,</hi> that the Covenant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111786:7"/> made <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.8.9.10.11.12.13.14. is a Covenant of Grace, which is a greater priviledg, then belonged to the seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Isaac</hi> after the flesh; and is opposite to the eternall truth of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.9. <hi>For they are not all Israell, which are of Israell, v.</hi> 7. <hi>Neither because the seed of Abraham are they called children: But in Isaac shall thy seed be called,</hi> 8. <hi>v. that is, they which are the children of the flesh they are not the children of God, but the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise they are accounted for the seed, Gal.</hi> 3, 9.26.28.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.9.10.11.12.13.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Because this popish consequence of the Baptizing (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers declareth that grace is entayled to generation, and not to regeneration; which doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the word of Christ, <hi>John</hi> 3.5.6. <hi>That which is borne of the flesh is flesh; and that which is borne of the spirit is spirit; marvell not that I say vnto you, that you must be borne againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleevers holdeth forth, that all the Infants of the beleeving Gentiles have a right to a promise of life in Christ Jesus before faith received, which opposeth the written Word, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. The Scriptures concludeth all vnder sin, that the promise by the faith of Jesus Christ might be given to them that beleive, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>as many as received him to them he gave power to be called sons of God even to them that beleive in his name:</hi> 13. <hi>which were not borne of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers holdeth out, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Beleivers may be saved by their parents faith, which is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite to the sacred word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The just shall live by his faith, Gal.</hi> 3.11.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or rather sprinkling of the Infants of Beleivers endangers to bring the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrators of Infants Baptisme vnder a dreadfull curse for entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the word <hi>seed,</hi> or <hi>children</hi> to have right to Baptisme, that God hath not added, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.28. <hi>If any shall adde to this thing, God shall adde to him the plagues written in this Booke. Gal.</hi> 1.9. <hi>If any preach vnto you any other Gospell, then that yee have received, Mar.</hi> 16.16.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111786:7"/>
               <hi>let him be accursed:</hi> and so discovereth him to be of the <hi>evill one, a liar Joh.</hi> 8.44. As wise <hi>Agur</hi> admonisheth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Adde not thou to his wods, least he reprove thee; and thou be found a liar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Because this popish consequence of Baptising (or rather sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers (as the Pope enjoyneth all his preists, that receive power and jurisdiction from and vnder him) first to Baptize (or rather sprinkle) them) and then to teach them: which doth flatly oppose the Commission granted by King Jesus to his Disciples, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Goe yee into all the World, and preach the Gospell vnto every creature: He which beleiveth, and is Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, shalbe saved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 Because this popish consequence of the Baptisme (or sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infant of a Beleiver declareth, that the Infants of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers are the subjects of Baptisme before faith and repentance is manifested, and confesse, which contradicteth the inspired Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Repent, and be Dipped everie one of you in the name of Jesus for the remission of sinnes. Act.</hi> 8.36. <hi>See here is water, what hindereth, but that I may be Dipped.</hi> 37. <hi>If thou beleivest with all thyne heart, thou mayst.</hi> He Answered, <hi>I beleive Jesus is the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Because this popish consequence of the sprinkling of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Beleivers doth vniversally oppose the order of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus granted by his commission, Mat. 28, 19. <hi>Goe yee and Disciple all Nations, Dipping them in the name of the father, sonne, and holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,:</hi> And the practice of the Apostolicall Churches, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. <hi>they which gladly received the Word, were Dipped, Act.</hi> 8.12.36.37.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47.48.16.15.33.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Because this popish consequence of the Baptizing (or sprinkling) of the Infants of Beleivers vpholdeth that vnsound doctrine of vniversall Redemption, to wit, that all baptized persons are saved: or else it will necessarily follow, that some may be in a state of grace in their minority, and fall away from grace in their seniority, which is opposite vnto the sacred Word, <hi>Psal.</hi> 92.13. <hi>Such as be planted in the House of the Lord, shall florish in the Courts of our God, and they shall still bring forth fruit in old age, and be fat and florishing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. Because this popish consequence of the baptizing (or sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111786:8"/> of Infants of Beleivers vpholdeth the accursed doctrine of Rome: to wit, that the Sacraments conferre grace <hi>ex opere operato</hi> by the worke done: <hi>Ber,</hi> the Minister acknowledgeth, before he sprinkled it (that it was borne in sinne, and a Child of wrath, which is as cleare a truth as any in the Scriptures, <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.5, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.3.) But when he hath prayed over it, and taken it vp in his Armes, and blessed it, and sprinkled it in the name of the Father, and of the sonne, and the Holy Spirit; then it is regenerate, and borne a new of water: and of the Holy Spirit, and grafted into the body of Christs Congregation, and made a lively member of the same.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Because this popish Consequence of the Baptising (or sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infants of Beleivers opposeth the Kingly and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Office of Jesus Christ in faith and Order.</p>
            <p>First, Christ requireth, that the subject that is to be dipped, be a Beleiver; that is, to be converted to the faith of Jesus Christ through the preaching of the Gospell, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Goe yee into the World, preach the Gospell to every Creature: He which Beleiveth and is dipped shalbe saved, Act.</hi> 8.12.35.36.37.38.10.44.37.47.48.16. c. 14.15.30.31.32.33.34.</p>
            <p>Secondly the Order of Jesus Christ was, that the beleiver, that manifested his faith, and repentance should be dipped, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Disciple the Nations Dipping them in the name of the father, the son, and the holy spirit. Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Repent and be Dipped every one of you in the name of &amp;c. Act.</hi> 8.12.36.37.38.10.44.47.48.16.14.15.33. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.5. <hi>one faith, one dipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that the Learned English Ministrie would timely consider, (what a dangerous thing it is to hault betwixt two) and remember <hi>Elijah</hi> speech, <hi>If God be God follow him, if Baal then follow him,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.21. Knowing what the Lord Jesus saith; <hi>No man can serve two Masters, he will love the one and hate the other, Luke</hi> 26.13. to this <hi>Paul</hi> admonisheth to take heed: <hi>For there is no agreement betwixt light and darkenesse, Christ and Belial, the Temple of God and Idols.</hi> Oh that you had an heart to obey the voyce that followeth, <hi>Come out from amongst them my people, touch not the vncleane thing, and I will receive you,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.16.17. Least for contemning the eternall Commission of Jesus Christ (<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18.19.20.) yee heare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111786:8"/> that dreadfull voyce, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>These mine enemies that would not that I should raigne over them, bring them hither, and sley them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As also for contemning his propheticall Office. Seeing the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Heaven commandeth vs to heare his Sonne, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5. The Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> tels vs the extent: how farre we should heare him, <hi>In all things whatsoevrr he shall say vnto you.</hi> The danger followeth. <hi>And it shall come to passe, that everie Soule, that will not heare the voyce of that Prophet, shall be destroyed from amongst the people, Acts</hi> 3.22.23 Oh let vs not feare them that can kill the body, they can doe no more. But let us (my deare Countreymen) feare to displease this Great King and Prophet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, that can cast Body and Soule into Hell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.</p>
            <p>My third Reason (why I deny this popish consequence) is this.</p>
            <p>That Consequence which is upheld by the Traditions of men, is destructive to the Nationall Covenant of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> ratified by an Ordinance of Praliament.</p>
            <p>But this popish Consequence of the Baptisme (or rather sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) of the Infants of Beleivers is upheld by the Traditions of men.</p>
            <p>Ergo this popish Consequence of the Baptizing (or rather sprinkling) the infants of Beleivers is destructive to the Nationall Covenant of England and Scotland, ratified by an Ordinance of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Major is evident: Pecause the Nationall Covenant bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to stand for a thorough Reformation in Religion in England and Ireland, in Doctrine, Worship, Discipline, and Government, according to the Word of God, and the Example of the best reformed Churches, which is the primative patterne foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the Word of the eternall truth, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.20. As Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wilson</hi> a member of the Synod affirmed, when he preached, and pressed, the takeing the Nationall Couanant at <hi>Town-mauling</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> And to exterpate Popery, Prelacy, Superstition, Heresy, Scisme, and whatsoever shall be found contrary to sound Doctrine, and the power of godlynes, that the Lord may be one and his name
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111786:9"/> one in the three Kingdomes. To confirme the truth of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, these select portions of holy Scripture beareth record, <hi>Esa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.34.8. 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.10.11.</p>
            <p>Minor is as evident, that the Baptisme or sprinkling of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Beleivers is but a Tradition of men, <hi>August. de Bap. contra Donat. l.</hi> 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 23. <hi>Origen in Levit. Hom.</hi> 8. <hi>in Epist. ad Rom. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rasmus lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de ratione concionandi;</hi> saith, <hi>That they are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, that doubt whether Infants Baptisme were ordained by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.</hi> The Papists themselves from whom we derive the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the Baptisme of the Infants of Beleivers, openly professe, that the Baptisme of the Infants of Beleivers is grounded on Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and not on the Scriptures, <hi>Bellar. lil.</hi> 4. <hi>he verbo Dei cap.</hi> 9. Mr. <hi>Dan. Rogers</hi> in his <hi>Practicall Catechisme on the two Sacraments</hi> saith thus, <hi>I take the baptizing of Infants to be one of the most reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, generall, and vncontrouled Tradition (which the Church hath) and which I no lesse doubt of, then the Creed to be Apostolicall, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I confesse my selfe yet vnconvinced by demonstration of Scripture for it.</hi> Now seeing it is confessed by the Learned on both sides, that it is but a Tradition; Oh let it never be said of the Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of England, nor of the Learned Ministrie of our Nation (as Christ said of old of the <hi>Pharisies</hi>) full well ye reject the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, that you may keep your owne Traditions, least the sword goe through the Land to avenge the quarrell of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. that was made to stand for a Reformation in Doctrine and Worship in England and Ireland according to the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If Baptisme succeed Circumcision; then to the same persons, vpon the same Commandement, vpon the same day, and vnder the same penaltie, or els it is no succession. Then it will necessarily follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That none but males must be Dipped, so all females are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which opposeth the scared Word, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12. when they belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Phillips</hi> preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of God, and the name of the Lord Jesus, they were Baptized both men and women.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They must be Dipped the eight day: or els the penaltie will follow; the vnbaptized or vndipped Infant shalbe cut off from his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111786:9"/> people: he hath broaken my Covenant, <hi>Genesis</hi> 17.14</p>
            <p>To reforme any errour crept into the Churches of the Old and New Testament, it was their holy custome to reduce all things to their first Institution, <hi>quod primum virum,</hi> according to <hi>Tertullians</hi> judgment: As <hi>David</hi> in the miscarige of the <hi>Arke,</hi> 1 <hi>Cro.</hi> 15.2.12.13. And zealous <hi>Josiahs</hi> rule (whom the spirit of God so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth in Scriptures, that none was the like before him for his Reformation, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 34.31. And as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did after his returne from the <hi>Babylonish Captivity, Nehem.</hi> 10.29. They clave to their Bretheren, their Nobles, and entered into a Curse, and an oath to walke in Gods Law, which was given by <hi>Moses</hi> the servant of God, and to observe, and doe all the Commandements of the Lord our God, and his Judgments, and his Statutes. So is the reforming of the particular Churches of the New Testament, whereof Jesus is head, King, and Prophet; and (if ever she be rightly brought out of her spirituall Babylonish Captivity) we must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme as the Lord Jesus hath left vs a rule, about the regulating of that long spread errour of <hi>Lygamie,</hi> and <hi>Polygamie;</hi> refuting the <hi>Pharisies</hi> (though he had a Toleration by a Law from <hi>Moses</hi>) with a <hi>non fuit fic ab initio, from the beginning it was not so, Mat.</hi> 19.7.8, yea and we must so follow the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> (as he followed Christ, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.) in reforming the abuses crept into the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> reducing all to the first Institution, with a <hi>what I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Lord, that I delivered vnto you,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. And not be carried away with the corruptions of evill times, under the specious pretence of Antiquity, Vniversality, Vnity; the three great Pillars of the Roman Hierarchie; looking more after Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> resolution, that he gave to <hi>Austen</hi> the Monke and Arch-Bishop of Canterburie, that in case of necessity the Infant might be baptized as soone as it were borne, <hi>An. Christi</hi> 599. as Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> in his Booke of Martyrs relateth.</p>
            <p>Or what Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third decreed, <hi>Detret. Greg. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 42. <hi>c.</hi> 3. as Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> in his <hi>Synopsis Papismi de Baptismo Infanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> recordeth.</p>
            <p>Then what the Lord Jesus (that Royall King of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (by his Commission hath commanded: <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.28. <hi>All pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111786:10"/> is given me in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> 19. <hi>Goe ye therefore; and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple all Nations, dipping them in the name of the father, and of the son, and of the holy spirit:</hi> 20. <hi>Teaching them to observe all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever I have commanded you, and loe I am with you alwayes vnto the ends of the world. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Commission is explained by King Jesus himselfe: How his Apostles should disciple the Nations, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.16. <hi>Goe ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the World, preach the Gospell vnto every Creature:</hi> 16. <hi>He that beleiveth, and is dipped, shalbe saved.</hi> To this exposition Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> agreeth in his Coment. on <hi>Gal. c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 27. on the forme of Baptisme; Make them disciples: to wit, Teach men to beleive and repent, and when men beleive and repent, then baptize them.</p>
            <p>They which despised <hi>Moses</hi> Law, and refused to conforme ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the patterne God left them by the hand of his servant <hi>Moses (who was faithfull in all his House, Heb.</hi> 3.) were ruined, both their Kings and Kingdomes, as appeareth, 1 <hi>King</hi> 17.5.6.7.8.9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The like hard thing befell <hi>Judah,</hi> for her corrupting the pure worship, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 36.14.15.16.17.18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How shall we escape, (if we neglect so great salvation) which at the first began to be spoaken of by the Lord, and was confirmed vnto vs, by them that heard him: God bearing them witnesse both with signes and wonders; and with divers miracles, and guifts of the holy Ghost, according to his owne will, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.4. Seeing the father from Heaven commandeth vs to heare him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. And <hi>Peter</hi> saith, Moses truly said unto the fathers, the Lord your God will raise vp a prophet from the midst of your brethren like vnto me; him shall ye heare in all things, whatsoever he shall say vnto you: And it shall come to passe, that every soule, that will not heare that Prophet, shall be destroyed from amongst the people Acts 3.22.23.</p>
            <p>Therefore I say unto you (my dear Countrey-men) Chuse you, whom you will serue, and obey; I and the Saints vnited with me, will serue the Lord Jesus only: as <hi>Joshuah</hi> told <hi>Israel, Josh.</hi> 24.15.</p>
            <p>My Reasons are these.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the Lord Jesus be not my Prophet to teach me, and the Saints vnited; he will not be our King to protect vs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.20.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111786:10"/>2. If he be not our Prophet to teach vs: he will not be our Preist to interceed for vs, <hi>John</hi> 17.20. <hi>I pray not for these alone, but for them also that shall beleive in me through their Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 If he be not our prophet to teach us: he will not be our Judge to acquit us, <hi>He which rejeteth me, and receiveth not my words hath one that judgeth him, the words that J have spoaken, the same shall judge him in the Last Day. John</hi> 12.48.</p>
            <p>But if I, and the Saints vnited confesse him, he will confesse vs before his father, in Heaven: <hi>Mat.</hi> 10, 32. But if we shall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of him, and his words, in this sinfull and adulterous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: he wilbe ashamed of vs, when he cometh in the glory of his father with his holy Angels, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.38.</p>
            <p>And what will it profit a man, or any of vs then; if we should gaine the world, and loose our owne soules? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soule, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.26.</p>
            <p>For I am assured, it will be said of me (whose eyes God hath opened to discerne this popish corruption,) if I should altogether hold my peace, and for filthy lucre sake, betray the liberty of the Gospell, despising the Kingly and propheticall Office of Jesus Christ, as Christ said once of Judas Iscariot in an other case, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.24. Goe thy wayes, it had been good for this man that he had never been borne: And because I received not the love of the truth that I might be saved: for this cause the Lord in Justice will give me vp to strong delusions to beleive a lie, that I might be damned, who beleived not the truth, that I might be saved but had pleasure in vnrighteousnes, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.10.11.12. And so justly perish with the Antichristian Synagogue, that denyeth that Jesus is the Christ, to wit, the eternall King, Preist, and Prophet: For they are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist, that denyeth the father and the sonne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22.</p>
            <p>Thus then I argue in the defence of Jesus my King, and Prophet.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That way that Jesus Christ as Head and King hath constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Church, that is the way for all Beleevers to take vp, and walke in.</p>
            <p>But by teaching the Gospell and Dipping, Jesus Christ as Head and King hath constituted his Church.</p>
            <p>Ergo, teaching the Gospell, and Dipping is the way for all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers to take up and walke in.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111786:11"/>
            <p>Major is evident, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>I am the way, the truth and life, no man can come to the Father but by me, John</hi> 10 9. <hi>I am the Dore, by me if any enter, he shall be saved, and shall goe in and out and find pasture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Minor is as cleare, <hi>Marke</hi> 1.14. Jesus came into Galilee preaching the Gospell of the Kingdome of God: 15. Saying repent ye and beleive the Gospell. 16. He called Symon and Andrew: Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men. Their faith was manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>v.</hi> 18. they streight way left all, and followed him. 20. <hi>John</hi> 4.1. The Pharises heard, that Jesus made and Dipped more Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples then John.</p>
            <p>That way the Apostles constituted their Churches, that is the way for all Beleivers to take vp and walke in,</p>
            <p>But by teaching the Gospell and Dipping, as Jesus by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission commanded, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.15.16.) the Apostles constituted their Churches.</p>
            <p>Ergo, teaching the Gospell and Dipping (as Jesus by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.16. hath commanded) is the way for all Belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to take vp, and walke in</p>
            <p>Major is evident, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. Be ye followers of me as I am of Christ. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. Brethren be ye followers of me, and marke them that walke so as ye have vs for an ensample.</p>
            <p>Minor as evident, Goe ye into all the world, preach the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to every creature. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. He which beleiveth, and is dipped, shall be saved.</p>
            <p>Acts 2.38. Repent and be Dipped every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sinnes, and ye shall receive the guift of the holy Spirit.</p>
            <p n="39">39. For the promise is to you, and to your children, and to all that are a farre off, even as many as the Lord our God shall call.</p>
            <p>Now that neither the Jew, nor his children hath a right to the the promise of life in Christ before calling; it is cleare, if you compare this first Text, Acts 2.39. with Heb. 9.15.</p>
            <p>And for this cause Jesus is the Mediatour of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that by meanes of death for the redemption of the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions that were vnder the first Testament, they which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led might receive the promise of eternall Inheritance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111786:11"/>
            <p>Acts 2.41. Then they which gladly received the word were Dipped, and the same Day were added to them (to wit, the 120. persons, Acts 1.15.) three thousand soules.</p>
            <p n="43">43. And they continued in the Apostles Doctrine and fellowship, in breaking of bread and prayres, &amp;c. Acts 8.12.10.44.47.48.16.14.15.31.32.33.34</p>
            <p>There were women in the first constituted Church after the Apostollicall Order: Acts 1.14. and had a right to the breaking of bread as well as the men.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thus I oppose the Antichristian faction that denyeth that Jesus is the Christ, 1 John 2.22.</p>
            <p>They which enter into Church fellowship other wayes, then Jesus Christ and his disciples entered, are theeves and robbers.</p>
            <p>But Pope Innocentius the third and his followers entered into their fellowship otherwayes, then Jesus and his Disciples have entered.</p>
            <p>Ergo, Pope Innocentius the third, and his followers, that are entered into their Church fellowship are theives and robbers.</p>
            <p>Major is evident, John 10.1. He which entereth not by the dore of the Sheepfold, but climeth up some other way; the same is a theife and a robber.</p>
            <p>Minor as evident.</p>
            <p>They which enter not into their Church-fellowship by teaching the Gospell and Dipping (as Jesus and his Disciples entered) are theeves and robbers.</p>
            <p>But Pope Innocentius and his followers are entered into their Church-fellowship not by teaching the Gospell, and Dipping as Jesus and his Disciples entered.</p>
            <p>Ergo, Pope Innocentius and his followers that are entered into their Church-fellowship, are theives and robbers.</p>
            <p>Major is evident, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3, 16. And Jesus when he was Dipped went up streight way out of the water; And loe the Heavens were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto him: and he saw the spirit of God Descending like a Dove, and lighting vpon him: And loe a voyce from Heaven saying, this is my beloved sonne in whome I am well pleased.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 1.3.1. J knew him not: but that he should be made manifest vnto Israell, therefore am I come Baptizing with water: 32.33.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:111786:12"/>
            <p>Acts 2.41. <hi>Then they which gladly received the Word were dipped, and the same day were added to them</hi> (to wit, to the 120. persons amongst which were divers women with Mary, the mother of Jesus <hi>Acts</hi> 1, 14.15.) <hi>three thou-sand soules, and they continued in the Apostles in breaking bread and prayers, Acts</hi> 8.12.10.44.47.48.16.14.15.31. <hi>doctrine, and fellowship</hi> 31.32.33.34.</p>
            <p>Minor. I doe desire my deare and native countrey men with their learned Ministrie (that are in covenant with our Parliament wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, for a thorough Reformation according to Gods Word; And to extirpate all poperie, superstition, scisme, heresie; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is found contrarie to sound doctrine and the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, seriously, and timely to consider with themselves, whether the Congregations in England be constituted by the preaching of the Gospell, and Dipping? as the Lord Jesus the great King and Prophet by his Commission hath commanded and established, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. or not rather, as the Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an popish faction in corrupt times decreed.</p>
            <p>That by bethinking themselves, they never side with Antichrist any more, to oppose them that stand up for the gathering of Churches according to the Commission of King Jesus, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.19.20. as learned <hi>Gamaliel</hi> advised, least we be found fighters against God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.34, 45.36.37.38.39. but rather to become protectors of all such as are resolved to keep their Protestation and covenant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the oath they have taken (that God may make good his word to our Parliaments, as he promised to <hi>Asa,</hi> and they in part have found it, 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 15.2.) and to depart out of the spirituall and Mysticall Babylon according to Gods call, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.5. And be vnequally yoaked no more, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.15.16.17.18. that God may be a father to us, and to our distressed and distracted Land in these bloody dayes; and we may be his sonnes and daughters: And let vs never forget the words of our deare Redemer, <hi>John</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me, he will keep my words, and my father will love him, and we will come vnto him, and make our abode with him:</hi> Least we bring our soules vnder a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Anathama, Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p>Your pore despised countreyman that is willing to be reformed of any errour; if he shall from the word of the inspired Scriptures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111786:12"/> be rightly informed (from under the hand of any learned pen) that he is in an errour: Otherwise he is resolved to hold forth this truth in practice, and to stand for a Reformation according to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word in his native countrey: And to extirpate all heresie, and scisme with the pruning knife of Excommunication (that is not according to sound doctrine, and the power of godlynesse, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. out of the particular Congregations of Christs body: Though for the maintenance of the said truth, he suffer many hard things by his owne countrey men, as in part he hath done already: yet I am perswaded, that none that love and feare King Jesus will ever consent vnto it: For I am confident, If I should altogether hold my peace at this time, light would bring up to the pore scattered Saints in England (that have long lay under spirituall Babylonish Captivity) an other way: but I shall perish, and who koweth whether my life were preserved for the discoverie of such a popish errour (as <hi>Mordecai</hi> told <hi>Hester</hi> in an other case, <hi>Hest.</hi> 4.14.) as this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Search and see, you noble and Hierical English Covenanters, who cause divisions and offences amongst you, Rom.</hi> 26.17.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8.9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.4.5. 2 <hi>John</hi> 3.10.11. <hi>And from such withdraw: Least yee incurre the high displeasure of Great King Jesus, Luke</hi> 10.27.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>